Monica Daley (she, her): Emily, can you hear me?
Emily Smith: I can.
Monica Daley (she, her): Wow!
Emily Smith: How are you?
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm doing. Okay, how are you?
Emily Smith: Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): Did you get your?
Monica Daley (she, her): You were working on a poster. Did you get that finished?
Emily Smith: I did, and I presented it at the beginning of the month at Ispgr. So.
Monica Daley (she, her): Did it go? Okay.
Emily Smith: I thought it went well, okay.
Emily Smith: I got it together. It was.
Emily Smith: It was not together when you saw it, and I got it together.
Monica Daley (she, her): It was a little bit stressful. Huh?
Emily Smith: It's good. I think I'm gonna use it as kind of
Emily Smith: not exactly the same thing, but pretty much the same idea for my 1st aim for my calls proposal. So.
Monica Daley (she, her): And.
Emily Smith: I was grateful to have the time to talk through it with people.
Emily Smith: Low stakes, you know.
Emily Smith: It was nice.
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm afraid what I was planning to go through today will be way too basic for you.
Emily Smith: I'm just here.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay.
Emily Smith: Expectations.
Monica Daley (she, her): I can get into more advanced emg stuff depending on who's actually here. But.
Emily Smith: I'm here for.
Monica Daley (she, her): Hi Lauren.
Lauren Infantino: Hey? How's it going.
Monica Daley (she, her): Now I feel like I need to go dig up my more advanced code to be as now that you 2 are here.
Emily Smith: No nonsense.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, I'm here for whatever you have planned.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay. So if you are here, let me see, I'm gonna try to send you
Monica Daley (she, her): a link to the file. Some files that we're going to be using as examples. Just hold on for a minute.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, I'm gonna put a link in the chat
Monica Daley (she, her): and that should go to a folder that has 2 example scripts and and 2 example data files that you should download to your computer.
Monica Daley (she, her): did you get a link to that.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, do it?
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, then, let's see.
Monica Daley (she, her): Can you see my desktop? Now.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay with the Matlab.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, with, both screens. Open.
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh, it has. I've got the script on one side. I've opened here the 1st example, I think.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then I've got the Workspace over here, and you should, once you've downloaded your the example files. Go to the file browser in Matlab and make sure that you browse to
Monica Daley (she, her): the file location where you loaded, where you downloaded your files.
Lauren Infantino: So you can see them in the, in the file, in the current folder.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so
Monica Daley (she, her): first, st I was just going to sort of walk through an example data set. But there's maybe some
Monica Daley (she, her): I hope, some general principles that we can talk through along the way. But it would be helpful if maybe
Monica Daley (she, her): it's mo most helpful if this is interactive and actually focused on what you
Monica Daley (she, her): need to learn about emg filtering. So it's helpful to know what you're like, what
Monica Daley (she, her): past background, what past experience you have with filtering in general.
Monica Daley (she, her): What do you know about filters? So we can talk about filtering principles as well. So I'm gonna just stop sharing. So I can see your faces and stuff?
Monica Daley (she, her): How much experience do you have with filters
Monica Daley (she, her): previously? Have you used them? Have you written your own code?
Carissa J Mallonee: I have not.
Monica Daley (she, her): You have not okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): How many of you have heard of a Bodhi plot?
Monica Daley (she, her): No. And is Vanson there, can you? I don't know if Vanson's in a position to respond or not.
Vanson Vu: Yeah. Sorry. I was trying to download the files.
Vanson Vu: Okay. But have you ever heard of a bode plot?
Vanson Vu: I have not.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, we're gonna start there. All right. So filter design.
Monica Daley (she, her): we're we're probably you've all seen lots of data over time. Right? But filter design.
Monica Daley (she, her): You don't. You know, we often don't look at it
Monica Daley (she, her): this way when we're actually just implementing filters, but it is sort of like the basis of the theory. In the background, all of the data is transformed into the frequency domain
Monica Daley (she, her): rather than in being operated on in the time domain. And I'm not going to go into all of the theory about that. But basically any signal, right? Theoretically, you can reconstruct that signal from a series of sine waves. Right? A sum of a series of sine waves at different frequencies and amplitudes. Right
Monica Daley (she, her): and filter design is basically based around that concept and the filter as the specification that it basically gets rid of the frequency in certain specified ranges and allows a pass through
Monica Daley (she, her): unchanged the components that are in another what is called the pass band. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And so
Monica Daley (she, her): if you were actually taking a a theory class on filter design, you would a lot of that would revolve around bode plots and understanding the frequency domain. I'm gonna see if I can do like a whiteboard. I am terrible at drawing on whiteboards, but we're gonna just try it. I can do one more whiteboards, new whiteboard.
Monica Daley (she, her): Can you see my whiteboard.
Monica Daley (she, her): All right.
Emily Smith: Yes.
Monica Daley (she, her): So a bodie plot, I'm just going to. Basically.
Monica Daley (she, her): there are 2 components to a bode plot. One looks at the magnitude of the filtered signal
Monica Daley (she, her): as a function of frequency. So we would have
Monica Daley (she, her): magnitude. I'm gonna just call M and frequency in Hertz, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And basically, you have a
Monica Daley (she, her): a frequency. That is the original magnitude of the original signal. We're gonna just like normalize hypothetically here, to one right
Monica Daley (she, her): is the original signal, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And so if the filter
Monica Daley (she, her): allows all of the signal at that frequency through then our frequency response of the filter will be at one meaning. There's no attenuation of frequencies at that of the signal at that frequency. Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): And this is plotted as a function of frequency. And so basically, you just imagine that you have reconstructed the original signal
Monica Daley (she, her): with sine waves of various frequencies. Right? You can plot the original data, using that, you can actually do that on the original data and plot the results which we can maybe work up to. But hypothetically, you can do that for any signal right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And what a frequency, what a filter does is, if you so, the the terms that you will see with filters are like.
Monica Daley (she, her): can I do a text box here because I am terrible at writing high, pass, low, pass
Monica Daley (she, her): and band pass.
Monica Daley (she, her): This terminology can be a little bit confusing. High pass means you filter out low frequencies.
Monica Daley (she, her): and you pass through.
Monica Daley (she, her): I frequencies. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay? So you use a high pass filter.
Monica Daley (she, her): For example, if you have motion artifact
Monica Daley (she, her): at low frequencies. But your actual signal is at higher frequencies. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): A low pass filter filters out 5 frequencies and passes through low frequencies.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): And the band pass applies both a high pass filter and a low pass filter on the same data. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And so it a lot passes through a specified
Monica Daley (she, her): frequency band. And that's why it's called. There's a band pass right?
Monica Daley (she, her): Though
Monica Daley (she, her): we can talk about. So you need to know something about the frequency characteristics of your signal and the likely frequency characteristics of the noise
Monica Daley (she, her): that you're trying to filter out of that signal right? And so some common sources of noise that we have to deal with in
Monica Daley (she, her): in filtering right are motion artifact. This is something like sometimes when we have emg electrodes on people
Monica Daley (she, her): or emg wires, it's more problematic with wired systems, because wires act as an antenna, and when they move that causes an emotion artifact in the signal
Monica Daley (she, her): so
Monica Daley (she, her): you can pick up motion artifact. Those would typically be at the frequency ranges of the motion. And so they're at lower frequencies like below 25 Hertz.
Monica Daley (she, her): the other common source of noise that you would find in many signals is the
Monica Daley (she, her): just electrical noise by picking up the A/C line voltage.
Monica Daley (she, her): which is at 50 hertz, or 60 hertz, depending on which country you live in right here. It's 60 hertz in the Uk. It's 50 hertz.
Monica Daley (she, her): but that means that you would have a characteristic noise that's oscillating around that frequency in the signal. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): another source of noise that you might encounter is if you are getting interference from some kind of radio signal.
Monica Daley (she, her): So, we've had this problem when we had a very strong local radio station near our lab.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so we were getting, we were picking up the actual radio broadcast, like broadcast signals in the emg recordings, which is a real pain in the ass. And we basically had to. They were so big and so strong the entire. They made a new building that was, the entire building was turned into a Faraday cage to try to insulate from those signals.
Monica Daley (she, her): But another source that's more common in our setups
Monica Daley (she, her): is that if we are measuring sono micrometry at the same time as emg, the sono micrometry system is sending ultrasound
Monica Daley (she, her): noise into the body which the Emg signal can pick up. And so you will sometimes have those frequencies they tend to be frequencies. I can't remember Lauren, if you remember offhand what those frequencies tend to be. But they're higher, like.
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm gonna say, above a thousand, maybe something like that.
Monica Daley (she, her): So you need to know something about your signal
Monica Daley (she, her): and what kind of things you're trying to filter out
Monica Daley (she, her): and keep in your signal. So what do we want to keep in so like common sources of noise we've mentioned. Right is motion.
Monica Daley (she, her): 60 hertz electrical radio and ultrasound.
Monica Daley (she, her): What we also need to know is, what's the physiologically relevant range of the signal we're actually trying to measure right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And for emg, that relates to the frequency characteristics of action potentials.
Monica Daley (she, her): And that is, you know.
Monica Daley (she, her): for very slow ones. Unfortunately, that overlaps with some of our sources of noise so slow, slow action potentials can be as slow as 20 Hertz.
Monica Daley (she, her): right? So there is data at like the 20 Hertz. But
Monica Daley (she, her): we can for our purposes sometimes say, well, we think that the physiological range is actually more like, you know, 90 hertz
Monica Daley (she, her): to 450 hertz, or something like that.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay,
Monica Daley (she, her): or very slow.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): So when we're doing designing filters. What this would look like, what a low pass filter would look like in a bode plot
Monica Daley (she, her): would be.
Monica Daley (she, her): You are trying to pass through frequencies at a certain specified range.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then a perfect filter. You'd basically say, Okay, I'm interested in frequencies above 60 hertz, maybe right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And above that frequency. I don't want to filter anything out, so I'm keeping it all in
Monica Daley (she, her): and below that frequency, I completely cut it out so that it's out down to 0, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So it would be like a perfect square wave.
Monica Daley (she, her): But in reality it's impossible to design filters that are perfect square waves. They don't have
Monica Daley (she, her): a perfect it's, you know, you would have to have like a
Monica Daley (she, her): a filter with an infinite number of terms in it which is, gets unruly. So when we specify filters, we specify the filter cutoff frequency, and we specify a filter order.
Monica Daley (she, her): the filter order, the higher the filter order, the sharper that it more closely approximates this kind of like square wave shape.
Monica Daley (she, her): The lower the order, the more it looks kind of just like a gradual signal like this.
Monica Daley (she, her): What that means is that
Monica Daley (she, her): you may be filtering out some of the data that's actually in your relevant frequency range, and you may not be getting rid of all of the noise.
Monica Daley (she, her): But there's a trade off, because if you have, as you get filter orders of higher and higher order, it tends to introduce artifacts into your filtered signal
Monica Daley (she, her): so you can get weird things like
Monica Daley (she, her): you might be filtering a force signal that
Monica Daley (she, her): maybe it goes from 0 up to a peak and then back down to 0.
Monica Daley (she, her): If you have a really high filter order that's trying to approximate things with
Monica Daley (she, her): too high an order of filter. It might do something like this
Monica Daley (she, her): to your data where it like adds some weird artifacts in there.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so that's something to look out for basically, filters can introduce
Monica Daley (she, her): artifacts into your data, especially if you are using filters that are too constrained in their cutoff in their filter order, cutoff frequencies, and the reason you might need a sharp filter
Monica Daley (she, her): is that you might have a case where the actual signal is very close in frequency to the noise.
Monica Daley (she, her): But if that's not the case, then it's better to use a lower order filter in general, because they end up providing smoother results with fewer artifacts.
Monica Daley (she, her): So that's an example like, so, band, I'm sorry I'm not.
Monica Daley (she, her): What did I do? I started erasing everything.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, I'm gonna start again here. But I'm gonna go. Okay, my graph.
Monica Daley (she, her): I don't know how to use this thing very well.
Monica Daley (she, her): Hey? Where did my drawing pencil go?
Monica Daley (she, her): It disappeared.
Emily Smith: -Oh! Now I have one.
Monica Daley (she, her): I think I have one, too.
Monica Daley (she, her): You're drawing. You're drawing now. I don't know. Maybe only one of us can draw at a time.
Lauren Infantino: We can go like this.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, you're you're you're drawing it again.
Monica Daley (she, her): So when we filter emg.
Monica Daley (she, her): you need to know something about how the data was collected.
Monica Daley (she, her): And you need to know, for example, if there was already filtering in hardware, because there often is some right.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so if there was some filtering and hardware that might
Monica Daley (she, her): reduce the need for you to filter it in software right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And you need to know your original sampling frequency.
Monica Daley (she, her): So if we're gonna I still don't have my
Monica Daley (she, her): tool back for some reason, but
Monica Daley (she, her): so I'm a little confused about that.
Lauren Infantino: Hmm.
Monica Daley (she, her): Why can't I?
Monica Daley (she, her): Hmm.
Monica Daley (she, her): hmm!
Monica Daley (she, her): What happens if I add a page? Do I get
Monica Daley (she, her): get all my tools there? No.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay. Well,
Monica Daley (she, her): But can you switch to a different tool
Monica Daley (she, her): if you switch to a different tool? Does it give me my tool back.
Emily Smith: I switched mine so I shouldn't have one anymore.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, I switched.
Monica Daley (she, her): You switched.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): And you can still see the pen tool.
Emily Smith: Mine doesn't. You're more.
Monica Daley (she, her): That's so bizarre.
Monica Daley (she, her): Why.
Lauren Infantino: Did you take.
Monica Daley (she, her): A wig.
Lauren Infantino: You could go into the like the top right corner, and then you can maybe change.
Lauren Infantino: The participants can edit, and that we can have cursors.
Lauren Infantino: and just maybe that would only give you the ability.
Lauren Infantino: Reason.
Monica Daley (she, her): But it doesn't seem to change which tools are available for some reason. Okay, I'm gonna just try again.
Monica Daley (she, her): New whiteboard.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, I'm starting again. Okay, so we're gonna go back to the same graph here just quickly.
Monica Daley (she, her): Frequency.
Monica Daley (she, her): In Hertz.
Monica Daley (she, her): okay? So what we're going to do is compare some different filtering settings for filtering emg from an example data set.
Monica Daley (she, her): This data set is like,
Monica Daley (she, her): a little too clean to be a good example almost. But what I had handy, so we'll just use it, anyway. But we're going to design
Monica Daley (she, her): a high pass filter. Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): Which means like, we said, we're going to filter out low frequencies
Monica Daley (she, her): and keep high frequencies, and then we'll compare that to a bandpass filter
Monica Daley (she, her): where we have a band. So the filter design is going to look something like this
Monica Daley (she, her): right where we're filtering out low frequencies. We're keeping some specified frequency range. And we're filtering out high frequencies. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): and we're also going to look at the frequency composition of the original data compared to our filter design. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): so I'm gonna go to the data. So if you want to follow along.
Monica Daley (she, her): you'll wanna make sure you downloaded the code and then open the 1st example. File
Monica Daley (she, her): and I'll step through to make sure everybody can follow.
Monica Daley (she, her): This is this has a weird warning when I open this file. But it's okay. So don't worry about that.
Monica Daley (she, her): I think it's just an artifact of how it was saved. Originally. This is data from Caitlin Bemis's most recent data collection. So
Monica Daley (she, her): here I'm going to share my desktop again.
Monica Daley (she, her): Can you see my 2 Matlab windows again?
Emily Smith: Yes.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, so I have just evaluated the 1st 2 real lines here. Okay, to load the data.
Monica Daley (she, her): You get a warning. But don't worry about that. What you should see is within your workspace.
Monica Daley (she, her): a data table that we're going to pull emg data from.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): So let me know when you got there, and that you confirm that you're able to successfully load the data.
Monica Daley (she, her): And if you wanted to just double click on that data. You can see the entire data table.
Monica Daley (she, her): It's got a lot of things. But we're just going to pull out column 7 and 8, which are which are the Emg
Monica Daley (she, her): channels?
Monica Daley (she, her): To have a look at the Emg data and practice filtering?
Monica Daley (she, her): Did it load for you?
Emily Smith: Oh, see!
Monica Daley (she, her): It does print some warnings. But just don't worry about those warnings.
Emily Smith: Got it.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): so you should always confirm this before hard coding a variable. But you would confirm it in this case by looking at the time. Vector.
Monica Daley (she, her): and you can take. But so I'm basically, I know that the sample frequency is 5,000 hertz here. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): you can. If in some cases, you know, calculate it directly from the time. Vector but sometimes it's not recorded. So you need to know it in your notebook or something like that.
Monica Daley (she, her): One thing to note is that when you're designing the filters in Matlab, you'll it always works from normalized frequencies, and the frequencies are normalized based on what's called the Nyquist frequency.
Monica Daley (she, her): The Nyquist frequency is divided is the sample frequency divided by 2.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so it's that that Nyquist frequency is like the theoretical limit of what frequencies you can analyze from a given data set.
Monica Daley (she, her): You can't reconstruct anything about a signal above the Nyquist frequency. Okay, without
Monica Daley (she, her): more sophisticated methods. There, you know, there are modern methods that even can try to do that. But we're operating using techniques that operate based on the Nyquist frequency. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): so we're line 16
Monica Daley (she, her): to 19 here, just pulling the data out of that data table so that they're just in the format of a standard array in Matlab
Monica Daley (she, her): and then creating a time vector
Monica Daley (she, her): for reference later. So I'm gonna just go ahead and highlight line 16 to 17 and evaluate them. Oops
Monica Daley (she, her): actually go up to 13, evaluate all the way from 13.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, so we want to make sure. We set the sampling rate.
Monica Daley (she, her): Create our Emg data array. So now you can see
Monica Daley (she, her): after evaluating those lines, I have an Emg data array. That is just it's a an N by 2 double with where N is. The number of time points in the original data set right and 2 is for the 2 emg columns.
Monica Daley (she, her): so the next line here is just getting information about the total number of samples and the total number of channels of my Emg data in case I needed to, you know, operate in a loop to process them separately or things like that.
Monica Daley (she, her): Now we're going to start specifying the characteristics of our filter. Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): And you can play around with this on your own and see what happens when you
Monica Daley (she, her): you know, adjust these frequencies.
Monica Daley (she, her): So we're going to use some tools in mat, some functions in Matlab, but Ord
Monica Daley (she, her): designs a filter, a Butterworth filter, and it specified the order and cutoff frequency needed, based on
Monica Daley (she, her): specified stop band and passband characteristics. Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): So the stop band is right above the stop band. You want to get rid of all of the signal. Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): And the passband is right. Sorry we're doing a high pass filter. So above the pass band you want to keep all the signal below the stop band. You want to remove all of the signal. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): if it were a low pass filter, it'd be the other way around.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay. But so stop band means that's the frequency that you want to filter out.
Monica Daley (she, her): If it's high pass, then it's below that frequency, you filter it out.
Monica Daley (she, her): If it's low pass, then it's above that frequency, you filter it out. The past band is the frequencies that you want to make sure that you maintain.
Monica Daley (she, her): And the reason that these aren't the same is because it's impossible to create a completely vertical filter. Right? So this is specifying basically
Monica Daley (she, her): how wide is that window where the filters attenuating the signal. And it's not all the way at one or all the way at 0. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): and the function filter order allows you to figure out what filter order and cutoff frequency gives you that filter performance. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): now, it is also possible to just directly
Monica Daley (she, her): specify your filter order and your cutoff frequency, and those are the things that you'll see reported in papers. So you might like recreate results from papers by specifying those. But it gives you less insight into what your filters actually doing right in terms of the actual frequencies kept and filtered out.
Monica Daley (she, her): So
Monica Daley (she, her): these attenuation, this Rs is stop band attenuation. So by how many decibels does the signal get attenuated in the stop band? 40 is a lot that should be like basically removing it.
Monica Daley (she, her): and the rip past bend ripple. Basically, there's some basically remaining
Monica Daley (she, her): artifacts in the past band. And it's specifying how small those need to be.
Monica Daley (she, her): But these are pretty standard values. The actual default values, I think, are 40 and 3. But but you can read about more about those in the the help if you're interested. So I'm just gonna evaluate
Monica Daley (she, her): lines 32, 36 here or no. Sorry. 27 to 36.
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh, I need to go higher. I should have just done it by sections, right? I'm gonna just run the whole section
Monica Daley (she, her): which you can do, too.
Monica Daley (she, her): But then we'll walk through the different results. So first, st we're specifying our stop band and pass band frequency.
Monica Daley (she, her): I've put the stop end at 30 to remove all motion artifact associated with movement right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And the past ben at 90 just because I want to.
Monica Daley (she, her): If there's any 60 hertz noise I want to filter that out. But I want to keep
Monica Daley (she, her): the low, you know, motor like the the slow motor unit action potential activity as much as I can. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): If you then you got. You've got to normalize
Monica Daley (she, her): these frequencies to the Nyquist frequency, which is the sample frequency divided by 2.
Monica Daley (she, her): So that's what these this part is doing.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then the output of this function is the filter order, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And the cutoff frequency
Monica Daley (she, her): that I need to get that filter performance. So that cutoff frequency is in normalized units if we go. So I've recalculated it
Monica Daley (she, her): in Hertz by multiplying it back
Monica Daley (she, her): by the Nyquist frequency. And you can see that the effective cutoff frequency is 75. So it's telling me to get the performance I specified. I need a Butterworth filter of Order 5 and cutoff frequency of 75 hertz.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): And then you apply the filter using the function filt filt.
Monica Daley (she, her): you put in the outputs of this butter function right? B and A are simply the filter coefficients that
Monica Daley (she, her): were designed to meet the specifications.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then you put this into filt filt
Monica Daley (she, her): with your emg data and you get your raw data. I mean your filtered data out, okay as the output.
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm not plotting it yet, because I was going to plot them all together, but you could go ahead and do a quick plot. If you want of your just
Monica Daley (she, her): can work up to that. If we
Monica Daley (she, her): figure sorry. I mean to type, figure.
Monica Daley (she, her): If we just want to plot some of our filtered data and our raw data overly into the same plot, we can do a quick
Monica Daley (she, her): plot.
Monica Daley (she, her): Can you see my plot?
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, this did. As I said, the data, we're almost too clean. So you have to zoom in to see the difference between the filtered and the raw data.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so if you zoom in.
Monica Daley (she, her): what are the main difference, you what's the main difference? You can see here.
Lauren Infantino: Just looks like they're offset from each other.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah, so mainly the original raw in black had an offset, so it wasn't centered around 0. It had DC offset.
Monica Daley (she, her): If you apply a high pass filter, it always removes the DC offset. So that's important to note right? Because that DC offset is basically a low frequency component of of 0 herpes, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): That it's getting removed.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, so this was a pretty clean signal to begin with.
Monica Daley (she, her): so it didn't really change much.
Monica Daley (she, her): You look here, where there's a lot of action, you can see the baseline is pretty clean.
Monica Daley (she, her): Sometimes you see a lot more noise. It turns out that this one did have a 60 Hertz notch filter in hardware. So it did. It did minimize some of the noise in the in the data collection.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, so what about? So that's the high pass filter. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): in this case, it's just removing mainly removing the DC offset. It doesn't change things. But we could play around with different filter settings and see how it changes the output. And I encourage you to do that to get an intuition about how to how filters work, because you will also find that if you try to
Monica Daley (she, her): make these 2 frequencies too close, you'll get to a point where it can't actually create a filter that meets those specifications.
Monica Daley (she, her): So let's say, I was like, really like concerned, that there's real data
Monica Daley (she, her): at like the 60 Hertz range, or or something like that, and I tried to make these that a lot sharper.
Monica Daley (she, her): So let's say we want the passband to be 40 hertz rather than 90 Hertz.
Monica Daley (she, her): and we can go and just rerun this.
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm gonna just make this part its own section, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So we can rerun this section with different filtering settings. Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): And okay, it's still calculated the result in this case. So that's good.
Monica Daley (she, her): If you zoom in.
Monica Daley (she, her): you'll see that this one looks even more similar to the original. There's even less difference between the original and the raw data.
Monica Daley (she, her): But now, if we look at what our cutoff frequency is in the filter order
Monica Daley (she, her): oops the actual calculated.
Monica Daley (she, her): But our frequency in Hertz
Monica Daley (she, her): in this case it's doing a filter order of 19
Monica Daley (she, her): and a cutoff frequency of 38 to get that result.
Monica Daley (she, her): Usually there's no reason to do that unless you really have good.
Monica Daley (she, her): sound reasoning for it. Right? Because people tend to recommend that you use the lowest order filter that's adequate for your data set
Monica Daley (she, her): because of the potential for it to introduce artifacts into the signal.
Emily Smith: Monica.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah.
Emily Smith: If you're using something with that high of an order like, is that reliable data?
Emily Smith: Or do you.
Monica Daley (she, her): I mean, it doesn't have anything to do with the raw data. Right? This is just a filtering choice. But you can see. I mean, I think
Monica Daley (she, her): it's important to look at your filtered in your raw data and compare them right.
Monica Daley (she, her): and see if you're getting something weird that doesn't look real that you've introduced into the signal right? That's the main thing is like, do a reality check every time.
Monica Daley (she, her): you know I'm if I'm zooming in on this. This does not look problematic to me, because it seems to be following the original.
Monica Daley (she, her): Data pretty you know, accurately. So I'm not worried.
Monica Daley (she, her): I wish I had like a bad example to show you. But I would say where you typically see.
Monica Daley (she, her): the most obvious problems are
Monica Daley (she, her): when a signal rather than going sort of like symmetrically above and below 0. If you have a signal that goes from like 0 to a sharp kind of
Monica Daley (she, her): peak and then back to 0 and a sharp peak.
Monica Daley (she, her): What you might see is that in your filtered data.
Monica Daley (she, her): if you are using a high order filter, you will see it go below 0 and then up again. And so we'll introduce
Monica Daley (she, her): time points where the data goes. The filter data goes below 0, even though that was not in the original data. And if you see that, that's a problem, because that is actually introducing something, a feature into the data that wasn't originally there.
Monica Daley (she, her): So that's the thing to look out for.
Monica Daley (she, her): One thing you'll note. If you look in the literature, you'll see.
Monica Daley (she, her): that people often rectify emg signals because, the
Monica Daley (she, her): positive versus negative spikes aren't meaningful, right? And so they just show that rectified emg.
Monica Daley (she, her): It's important to. Not so don't do your high pass filter, after rectifying that will introduce some weird artifacts.
Monica Daley (she, her): Because that's when you'll get, because the whole signal is now above 0.
Monica Daley (she, her): Then you'll filter it with the high pass filter. It may introduce reintroduce cases where it goes below 0, because it's trying to fit that weird shape right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So when you are doing emg, filtering thus, the steps are to bypass or banned pass filter.
Monica Daley (she, her): The original raw data. Right? Then you can rectify it if you want to. To just show the like. Pot the the signal in in the positive only so we can walk through. That's what different sections of this.
Monica Daley (she, her): actually do so.
Monica Daley (she, her): There are some cases where you might want to bandpass, filter emg, and so I'm showing an example of a bandpass filter just for reference.
Monica Daley (she, her): The cases where you would most likely want to bandpass filter is, you know, for example, you might be getting
Monica Daley (she, her): interference from another signal that has higher frequency components like an ultrasound signal or something like that. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So in the bad past case, it's a little bit counterintuitive how you specify these filter settings. So that's why I wanted to provide an example. So if you look here at lines 54 to.
Monica Daley (she, her): or 54 and 55. I'm now specifying rather than one frequency for the stop band. There are 2 frequencies. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): so you can. Right now, it's set to below 30 hertz, and above 1,200 hertz. So that's
Monica Daley (she, her): just saying, this is like, if I had a case where
Monica Daley (she, her): I knew that there was some ultrasound interference
Monica Daley (she, her): that was in the sort of like 1,500 Hertz range, or something like that. Right? I might want to filter that out.
Monica Daley (she, her): So here
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm specifying stop. Band 30 and 1,200. The passband. Now remember, the passband is the signal, the range of the data you want to keep. Right, make sure you keep.
Monica Daley (she, her): and so we can specify. I have that at 90 here, to 800
Monica Daley (she, her): you could go narrower than that. But,
Monica Daley (she, her): you know it doesn't. There's no
Monica Daley (she, her): if there's no noise that's likely to be picked up at this sort of like higher frequency end, then you don't need to make that band too tight. Basically. So I've specified it as 800. We again need to normalize them based on the Nyquist frequency.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then, when you're running these same functions. See, I'm specifying the same functions. But in this case.
Monica Daley (she, her): if you are using a band pass filter, then it automatically knows it's a bandpass filter. If you have 2 frequency inputs for the parameters.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): So if I run this section.
Monica Daley (she, her): so we've got now, our stop band frequency has 2 numbers
Monica Daley (she, her): and our bandpass frequency. Then when we input these normalized frequencies into our
Monica Daley (she, her): butterworth filter order function, we get, we should get okay, we get a filter order
Monica Daley (she, her): of 9, and then our cutoff frequencies
Monica Daley (she, her): are 83, and 855, essentially, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So again, the filter order is like, how sharp does that filter roll, roll off right at the around the cutoff frequencies, and if you were
Monica Daley (she, her): looking at your this on a Bodhi plot.
Monica Daley (she, her): let's go back to the bode plot concept again. Real quick. Can you see the whiteboard?
Monica Daley (she, her): Did it? Just pop up? Okay,
Monica Daley (she, her): plotting these.
Monica Daley (she, her): This would be a bandpass filter.
Monica Daley (she, her): Your cutoff frequencies occur sort of right at the middle of that
Monica Daley (she, her): the slope where the frequencies are rolling off right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So the pass band would be like here, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): The stop would be like, so pass he stop. S, us, stop.
Monica Daley (she, her): And this would be these would be the cutoff frequencies. Z,
Monica Daley (she, her): okay, so your cutoff frequency is always going to be between your pass band and your stop band frequencies
Monica Daley (she, her): in the middle of this sort of roll off of that filter designed that you designed.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): So
Monica Daley (she, her): one other concept, that's important. So we we can, we're gonna plot the data. Let's go ahead and plot the data for our
Monica Daley (she, her): band pass results.
Monica Daley (she, her): Can you see the graph?
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): So if we zoom in
Monica Daley (she, her): one thing, you might notice in this one compared to the previous one is that the bandpass filter isn't attenuating the amplitudes of the spikes a little bit more than the original
Monica Daley (she, her): high pass filter did and the extent to which it does. That depends on how much
Monica Daley (she, her): real high frequency data there is in the signal
Monica Daley (she, her): relative to the bandpass frequency characteristics you specified.
Monica Daley (she, her): So we can play around with this. If you change this value, you could definitely make it
Monica Daley (she, her): so that there was a more obvious problem with your bandpass filter
Monica Daley (she, her): if you make those frequencies too low. So if we just run this one
Monica Daley (she, her): oops, I ran the whole thing. I didn't mean to read jumping ahead here. I mean meant to run this section only.
Monica Daley (she, her): So as you change those bandpass frequency characteristics, you'll get more pronounced attenuation of those higher frequency spikes right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And so that's another. You know, it's good to just look at your data and see if you make that too low. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So that's why it's important not to just use filter settings that other people have reported in the literature, but actually like.
Monica Daley (she, her): adjust the filter settings and look at your data and see how it correspond, how it looks in filtering your data. So if we run this section again.
Monica Daley (she, her): so if we put them low enough, you can see that there's obvious
Monica Daley (she, her): attenuation of real signal here, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And if you zoom in, you can see that the green one, the filtered one, is kind of lower frequency in characteristic, it's less. The spikes are less sharp.
Monica Daley (she, her): right? And that's because of the band pass filter. Right? So because we've put the the
Monica Daley (she, her): filter for the higher frequencies too low.
Monica Daley (she, her): So it's now attenuating that signal and getting rid of some signal. That's actually the real physiological signal.
Monica Daley (she, her): So this is also something that you would want to look at. If you're filtering force data, for example, force data is different from emg data in that you are typically
Monica Daley (she, her): running a low pass filter on the data to get rid of motion, artifact and electrical noise from the force data.
Monica Daley (she, her): But there are real
Monica Daley (she, her): higher frequency characteristics in force data, for example, around heel strike impact that actually do have some higher frequency components.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so when you're specifying your filters. If you're doing force data, you need to be careful that you.
Monica Daley (she, her): you know. Look at your filter settings carefully that it's not getting rid of some of the real force data in the signal that you might that might be relevant to your question.
Monica Daley (she, her): depending on what kind of question you're asking.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay? So we've done a band pass filter. I'm going to put it back at some
Monica Daley (she, her): more reasonable values. What did I have originally? 2,000?
Monica Daley (she, her): this is something I learned, you know, through trial and error, because if you look at the frequency settings that people mostly use for human emg data, it's lower frequencies than this.
Monica Daley (she, her): And I realized that guinea fowl mussels have higher frequency components than human muscles.
Monica Daley (she, her): So which isn't terribly surprising. I suppose they are smaller. But
Monica Daley (she, her): okay, so I'm reasonably happy with this version.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, where it's mainly removed. The DC offset of the signal. And if we zoom in here.
Monica Daley (she, her): even though it's attenuating some of those peaks slightly.
Monica Daley (she, her): it still retains the overall characteristics of the the curve. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So that's what I'm looking for. There.
Monica Daley (she, her): The other thing you'll often see in the literature on
Monica Daley (she, her): an emg, analysis is rectifying the emg and then doing a
Monica Daley (she, her): another low pass filter on the data. And this might be confusing, because it's like, well, why? I just filtered the data. Why do I need to filter it again? But the purpose of this version of the filter is very different. In this case.
Monica Daley (she, her): you're trying to basically estimate
Monica Daley (she, her): muscle activation characteristics or the time course of muscle activation based on the emg signal. Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): So because
Monica Daley (she, her): we we know that action potentials have this high frequency, component right? But muscles have excitation, contraction coupling that have basically
Monica Daley (she, her): smooth out effectively. The the development of forces at lower frequencies because of the delay associated with excitation, contraction coupling and so people have used
Monica Daley (she, her): a low pass Butterworth filter on the rectified signal to create what they call a smooth linear envelope.
Monica Daley (she, her): which basically approximates the timing of muscle activation from the emg signal.
Monica Daley (she, her): So the steps in doing that, you would want to do whatever
Monica Daley (she, her): filtering you need to on the original raw data before you rectify it. That might be a high pass filter or a band pass filter right? Depending
Monica Daley (she, her): here. And then
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm just putting the high pass filter data because we don't really have any noise of note up in the higher frequencies in this signal.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then I'm calculating a new Butterworth filter design that is, at 10 hertz
Monica Daley (she, her): so I'm normalizing 10 hertz by the Nyquist frequency.
Monica Daley (she, her): And I'm just using a second order specifying a second order.
Monica Daley (she, her): filter with a cutoff frequency of 10 hertz. So notice, I'm not going through all of the steps of the filter design, because I already know
Monica Daley (she, her): just this base. This is based on standard. You know, approaches in the literature on creating the linear envelope. To use
Monica Daley (she, her): it's a standard approach is to use a 4th order, low pass filter with a 10 Hertz cutoff. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): and different people might use slightly different values for that. But you could look in the literature to see.
Monica Daley (she, her): Although, I said, 4th order. I'm putting it as a second order in here, because when you run the function filt filt, it runs the filter forward and backwards on the same signal.
Monica Daley (she, her): and the resulting order is twice the original order. So if you run filt filt using a second order filter design, the resulting order is
Monica Daley (she, her): 4, and that's a little bit confusing. But
Monica Daley (she, her): okay, so if I run that section, I'm just basically running this filter on my rectified emg.
Monica Daley (she, her): And now I'm going to plot the results in a big tiled plot for all of the things that we've done. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): so we can see them all side by side.
Monica Daley (she, her): So this is just the data as a function of time.
Monica Daley (she, her): The top contains our raw data and the high pass filtered versions channel one is on the left channel 2 is on the right.
Monica Daley (she, her): You can see that channel 2. That muscle is much more active in whatever behavior we're measuring here, which is balancing on an unstable perch.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then the middle panel has the bandpass filtered characteristics, and the bottom panel has our linear envelope
Monica Daley (she, her): with the rectified signal.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): so if we zoom in, I've also used the function link axes. So if you if I go and zoom in on one graph.
Monica Daley (she, her): The X scaling will be maintained between the graphs.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so you can see this magenta colored curve is approximating the timing of activation. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): That's what's called a smooth linear envelope.
Monica Daley (she, her): Notice that it misses some important features, though.
Monica Daley (she, her): if you want to be picky
Monica Daley (she, her): it doesn't accurately capture these bursts here right.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so one of the criticisms of this smooth, linear envelope approach
Monica Daley (she, her): is that you are, in fact, applying a low pass filter to the data which therefore, attenuates high frequency
Monica Daley (she, her): components of the signal more than lower frequency components of the signal.
Monica Daley (she, her): So it actually better approximates the timing of the slower action potential components compared to any fast action potential components.
Monica Daley (she, her): And I don't have an example ready today. But one of the ways around that is
Monica Daley (she, her): to is that there's a different approach to calculating a linear envelope using wavelets.
Monica Daley (she, her): Where you use a bank
Monica Daley (she, her): of filters rather than just a single filter.
Monica Daley (she, her): And that bank of filters are wavelets that are designed to match the frequency, the range of physiological frequencies of action, potentials in muscle
Monica Daley (she, her): from around 20 hertz all the way up to 450 Hertz. So you get this bank of wavelets. And you can calculate from that, you basically use each wavelet to do a bandpass filter on the data.
Monica Daley (she, her): and then you sum the magnitudes across all of those wavelets to get your smooth linear envelope across all frequencies.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then, if you did that
Monica Daley (she, her): it would capture it should capture the activation associated with these little bursts, as well as like the general time course of activation for the whole cycle.
Monica Daley (she, her): All right.
Monica Daley (she, her): Do you have specific questions or specific tasks you're trying to accomplish with your data analysis.
Emily Smith: I admittedly have not been focused on emg in a couple of months. So I just yeah for general.
Emily Smith: And like.
Monica Daley (she, her): General, yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): Well, if if any of you are interested in doing like trying the wavelet technique on your data, we could do another session later on in the summer and actually run that on the data.
Monica Daley (she, her): It's something that can be useful
Monica Daley (she, her): if you're interested in the frequency composition
Monica Daley (she, her): of the motor, like the and the distribution of potential action potentials from slow to fast. And whether or not that changes in your data over over diff for different tasks as well.
Monica Daley (she, her): But it's a little bit more advanced in terms of a filtering technique, right?
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, think I'd I'd be interested in in doing that.
Lauren Infantino: cause I've been interested in, I guess, like muscle, fatigue, and the time. Course of that I feel like.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah.
Lauren Infantino: The wavelet analysis on that. In viewing, like throughout, a an activity.
Lauren Infantino: how does the frequency profile of the emg signal change in relationship to like
Lauren Infantino: the activity that somebody's doing. I think that's really interesting. So I think it would be cool to have a session on how to actually extract, like the frequency profile, especially from
Lauren Infantino: like, I guess the benefits of you know, you can like this data coming from the birds is.
Lauren Infantino: I think, how do you use
Lauren Infantino: surface emg signals, and how competent can you really be on.
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh, you're cutting off.
Lauren Infantino: Mg's versus like getting them when you're like actually implanting them into the muscle tissue.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah. So one thing you'll notice.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah, the frequency distributions will be a little bit different from surface emg versus indwelling. Emg, and.
Lauren Infantino: Like, how do you, I guess, make sure that you're correctly characterizing those profiles with surface emgs.
Monica Daley (she, her): I think you have to accept that they're going to be some limitations. So, for example, in the data I just showed you, we sampled at 5,000 hertz.
Monica Daley (she, her): usually with the surface emg you're going at like 1,000 or 2. How 1,000 Hertz. So you're not going to get.
Monica Daley (she, her): You're potentially losing some of the high frequency components.
Monica Daley (she, her): But in general, you know.
Monica Daley (she, her): I think, that there's been shown to be a reasonably good correspondence between surface emgs and indwelling electrodes. But the problems you have to deal with. There are
Monica Daley (she, her): crosstalk
Monica Daley (she, her): between muscles potentially right, and you will get a slightly different signal depending on how close you are to.
Monica Daley (she, her): You know the actual like.
Monica Daley (she, her): You know
Monica Daley (she, her): where the nerve is interfacing with the muscle itself. Right? The the nerve, the motor end plate with the muscle.
Monica Daley (she, her): So one way that people get around the crosstalk issue is, if I mean, and we
Monica Daley (she, her): we don't do this per se. But there are things called high density electrode arrays where you can basically
Monica Daley (she, her): have like multiple electrodes like a big array of electrodes on the muscle. And then if you have that, then people can actually like decompose the different components much like you do with Eeg. Right with Eeg. You put this array of electrodes on your head. And then you basically try to decompose the different spatial components based on that array of electrodes rather than interpreting the individual electrodes right?
Monica Daley (she, her): But in emg, we typically don't do that because usually
Monica Daley (she, her): you can, based on anatomical knowledge and placement of the electrodes, isolate things pretty well.
Monica Daley (she, her): So but that's you know something that you kind of have to
Monica Daley (she, her): like. If you're really, really, if it's really important that you know, you know exactly the frequency composition, and from individual muscles. You might have to do indwelling electrodes right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And and he.
Monica Daley (she, her): And it's possible to do indwelling electrodes in humans. But we typically try to avoid it because it's, you know, more invasive. And it hurts. Yeah.
Lauren Infantino: For the high density emgs.
Lauren Infantino: Can you like create almost like a pseudo one, if you just have, like bipolar electrodes and space them in an arrangement to where
Lauren Infantino: they're almost like a high density, correct.
Monica Daley (she, her): I suppose you could get, I mean, the more you can put more electrodes on, and then.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): You know, do you know some
Monica Daley (she, her): decomposition of the components that you and you know, measure from them like, look at the core. You'd basically be doing an analysis where you're looking at. You know the degree of correlation between the different pairings of electrodes right?
Monica Daley (she, her): And then doing a decomposition to try to get at the underlying components based on all of that analysis.
Monica Daley (she, her): So I'm not sure what the minimum would be to
Monica Daley (she, her): get. But I feel like if I were just to guess I feel like you'd need at least 8 electrodes to get a meaningful decomposition.
Monica Daley (she, her): and that sounds like a pain.
Monica Daley (she, her): Unless you're explicitly working with high density electrode arrays. And then that system would come with software that helps you with the decomposition process and stuff like that, too, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So you wouldn't have to invent it from scratch.
Lauren Infantino: I'm just curious.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): I do have an example from Delsis data as my example, too, if you want to go through that. But basically, it's exactly the same process, but on a different.
Monica Daley (she, her): on data that was collected using the wireless system.
Lauren Infantino: Hmm.
Monica Daley (she, her): If you want to open that file and look at it.
Monica Daley (she, her): But I think I mean, you've seen that kind of data plenty of times before. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): But if you want to, you can go ahead and open example 2.
Monica Daley (she, her): I don't know how long this office hour is supposed to go. But you know we could.
Monica Daley (she, her): We could try to do weight load analysis today if we wanted to.
Lauren Infantino: I'm fine.
Monica Daley (she, her): That would be me coding on the fly. But.
Lauren Infantino: I I was just wondering.
Lauren Infantino: is, I know there's a way to turn your like emg signal. Then straight into like free, like frequency on
Lauren Infantino: the x, and then the magnitude, or like, I guess.
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh, yeah, we didn't go through that part of my.
Lauren Infantino: And like is, would that be considered like.
Lauren Infantino: in another word, like the fast Fourier transformation sort of thing?
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, I forgot.
Monica Daley (she, her): Couple seconds
Monica Daley (she, her): of my script that I didn't go through that does that. If you want to go through and look at that real quick.
Lauren Infantino: Because, if you like, didn't know what frequency components or noise you had.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah.
Lauren Infantino: Be a way to.
Lauren Infantino: There's a way to look at that. So let's do that. So I understand. I see, yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah, so this is the bottom of the script has this. So we're gonna we can look at the data in the frequency domain. Okay?
Monica Daley (she, her): So the details here, like, basically, I'm just getting
Monica Daley (she, her): the inputs necessary to do a fast Fourier transform and plot the results. So fft is the fast Fourier transform function in Matlab.
Monica Daley (she, her): And I'm taking.
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm basically
Monica Daley (she, her): calculating the fft and then getting a magnitude from that so you can look up the help and read more about the fft function
Monica Daley (she, her): if you want
Monica Daley (she, her): So we're going. If you look at this part of the script.
Monica Daley (she, her): basically, what this is doing is it's getting the fft on the actual data.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then also, it's getting the filter frequency response from the bandpass filter that we created earlier, too.
Monica Daley (she, her): so that we can look at both the
Monica Daley (she, her): the actual data in one plot, and then the actual like frequency characteristics of the filter we designed in another plot.
Monica Daley (she, her): I couldn't get them to scale exactly the same way which is annoying me.
Monica Daley (she, her): But.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm gonna just run this section. You can step through if you
Monica Daley (she, her): like. If you have any questions about the steps we can. We can go through that. But if I run this section.
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh, something weird happened.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, it created 2.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay. Do you see this one.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, I must have used the figure.
Monica Daley (she, her): anyway. There's a slight bug in my code, but I haven't. But the basic plot is here. So in blue is the
Monica Daley (she, her): am I still here? Can you hear me.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, she did.
Monica Daley (she, her): My computer froze. So I feel like Zoom is about to crash on my computer. Possibly, does that happen sometimes.
Lauren Infantino: You're frozen, but I don't think your screen is.
Monica Daley (she, her): Weird.
Lauren Infantino: Think it's.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): So I might have to log out and try again if it gets.
Emily Smith: He may have disappeared.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): My computer crashed.
Monica Daley (she, her): Can you hear me.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, it is.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, I'm trying to reboot my desktop again. But yeah, that happens sometimes. Alright.
Monica Daley (she, her): is it still showing you did my shared screen and stuff. Go away.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah.
Emily Smith: Yes.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, let me.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay. Let's see if I can switch over.
Monica Daley (she, her): All right, I'm gonna try again.
Monica Daley (she, her): Let's see, my computer is still trying to sort itself out.
Monica Daley (she, her): sorry about that. So you were asking about frequency, looking at the frequency spectrum.
Monica Daley (she, her): I think that is actually really useful thing to do when you're trying to
Monica Daley (she, her): design your filter and think about what you whether you actually need any kind of fancy filtering at all. Right? In the 1st place.
Monica Daley (she, her): it's you know. You should probably keep it as your data processing as simple as you can, right? As simple as as, and not make it more complex than needed.
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm gonna try to run this again now. My computer's booted back up it working
Monica Daley (she, her): and share my screen again.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): so can you see this graph.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): Alright. So the blue is the
Monica Daley (she, her): frequent frequency distribution of the original Emg data, raw emg data.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then I've overlaid with lines the
Monica Daley (she, her): specified stop band and passband frequency characteristics.
Monica Daley (she, her): and I tried to lock these axes, but then I couldn't figure out why it's putting them on a linear scale on one and a log scale on the other. I don't know why
Monica Daley (she, her): I didn't have time to troubleshoot all of that. But the lines mean the same things on both. Right? So in the raw data here.
Monica Daley (she, her): you can see that my low free, my cutoffs here right for the low.
Monica Daley (she, her): Sorry. The the high pass
Monica Daley (she, her): cut off is these are really tight around a specified frequency range, and if I zoom in here
Monica Daley (she, her): you can actually see evidence that a notch filter was used in the data, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): Because you can see this dip here at 60 Hertz, right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So there is real frequency content across that range, and it has a dip at 60 hertz, which indicates that a notch filter was used to attenuate frequencies at that specific frequency. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): So you can kind of see a signature of the hardware filter in the data there.
Monica Daley (she, her): But then the peak of the real data, right. You can kind of see is sort of
Monica Daley (she, her): around the lower frequencies of the
Monica Daley (she, her): fast band range, but you can still see there's real content at higher frequencies as well.
Monica Daley (she, her): if you are getting into designing filters, you might want to go and look into decibels as a unit, because they're kind of confusing.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, what does it mean to have? Some of the signal frequencies are like in the negative disability.
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh, the decibels, I mean, yeah, I don't have a good handle on decibel magnitudes, but like it's not a linear scaling. It's a log based scaling.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so I can't remember, like orders of magnitude and decibels like
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh, decibels are kind of confusing, but it's like
Monica Daley (she, her): 2 signals whose level differ by one Decibel, have a power ratio of 10 to the 1 10.th
Lauren Infantino: Until one.
Monica Daley (she, her): change in power by a factor of 10 corresponds to a 10 decibel change in level.
Lauren Infantino: Hmm.
Monica Daley (she, her): It's a standard unit used in in frequency. But it's not one that I typically use. So
Monica Daley (she, her): a little confusing. But they also do hearing tests and decibels. Right?
Monica Daley (she, her): But the the main thing to think about is like, Okay, where do you see the most of your data, the real data.
Monica Daley (she, her): And how does that correspond to the cutoff filters? You've set? And then here, this is the showing, the design of the actual filter. You can see that. You know, it's going into the negative decibel range as well. But I think
Monica Daley (she, her): once you're getting down to like
Monica Daley (she, her): 40 decibels below like the original magnitude. You're basically getting rid of almost everything in that signal.
Monica Daley (she, her): So I don't think it's like
Monica Daley (she, her): super meaningful. Here we have. This is like magnitude 40 up here. Once we get to around 0. That's like there's nothing really there of note, right in in terms of magnitude.
Monica Daley (she, her): So if you have more complex.
Monica Daley (she, her): It might be useful to set this one aside, for now and then go look at the other data set for comparison.
Lauren Infantino: Hmm.
Monica Daley (she, her): You can
Monica Daley (she, her): we open example 2.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay,
Monica Daley (she, her): Do you have this example? 2 file.
Monica Daley (she, her): If you open up. Example 2,
Monica Daley (she, her): okay, we're. Gonna I'm just gonna run the 1st section open load the data.
Monica Daley (she, her): So you can see it has cleared my workspace. And now I just have the new data in the workspace.
Monica Daley (she, her): This is a data. This is from
Monica Daley (she, her): Vicon and Delsis data collection in the human performance lab.
Monica Daley (she, her): So and then in this case we have 8 emg channels from the Delta Cmg system.
Monica Daley (she, her): It's a wireless system, and this one
Monica Daley (she, her): actually has bandpass filtering in hardware.
Monica Daley (she, her): And I don't remember the exact frequency characteristics, but it is a pretty strong bandpass filter, so you don't get a lot of
Monica Daley (she, her): like noise from electrical signal noise and other and other sources. So in this case the main thing you want to do is remove potential motion artifact from the sensors moving on the body, for example, that might have if that introduced any crosstalk and the DC. Offset in the signal. And so here
Monica Daley (she, her): if we kind of know in this case
Monica Daley (she, her): the nature of the frequency, the of the motion artifact we want to filter out. We might just take a simpler approach to filtering, because this has a bandpass filter in the hardware.
Monica Daley (she, her): So in this case I'm just specifying. The filter order is 2. The cutoff frequency is 25 hertz and running a high pass filter on it. Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): section.
Monica Daley (she, her): Did I freeze again?
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh, my gosh.
Emily Smith: On my end.
Monica Daley (she, her): My computer is about to crash again.
Emily Smith: Oh, wait. Yeah, you froze. Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh!
Emily Smith: What if you turn your video? Well, I guess you can't turn your video off while you're sharing screen.
Emily Smith: Oh, pop up.
Monica Daley (she, her): My computer is totally.
Lauren Infantino: Maxed out.
Monica Daley (she, her): Well, it's because I turned out I had to install that zot defender software on and.
Lauren Infantino: That you can't uninstall something like that.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah, it's installed like, 19 background processes on my computer.
Monica Daley (she, her): And it's now cannot handle anything anymore.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, you can hear me, but still not see me.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, I can hear you. Your screen, I think, is frozen, though.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay, well, that might have to be it for today.
Lauren Infantino: Can run through this.
Emily Smith: Oh, this is nice!
Monica Daley (she, her): Let's see.
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh, wait, I can switch to this computer again. Let's see.
Monica Daley (she, her): Nope.
Monica Daley (she, her): Hello!
Emily Smith: Well.
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm sorry.
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm here.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): My other computer is frozen again. Unfortunately.
Monica Daley (she, her): So.
Monica Daley (she, her): Anyway, maybe we can. Oh, and it crashed, that is
Monica Daley (she, her): annoying. How am I supposed to teach with that computer now?
Monica Daley (she, her): I'm not sure that I can force it to stop sharing because my computer crashed.
Monica Daley (she, her): okay, well, sorry about the technical difficulties with my computer.
Monica Daley (she, her): It's like that's good to know that it's not
Monica Daley (she, her): that I can't rely upon it for for zoom stuff anymore.
Monica Daley (she, her): But all right. So maybe
Monica Daley (she, her): okay. Finally, it's shut down all the way.
Monica Daley (she, her): Do you have any general comments or questions
Monica Daley (she, her): for wrapping up? Maybe we can do.
Monica Daley (she, her): Lauren, do you have data that you'd like to do the wave load analysis on.
Monica Daley (she, her): To try it on.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, I can. I can get some data, try it on.
Monica Daley (she, her): Sorry.
Lauren Infantino: Oh, to him!
Monica Daley (she, her): My earbuds are not working.
Lauren Infantino: Can you hear me now?
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): Now, okay, now. So I just.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, I do.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yes.
Lauren Infantino: I have some data that. Yeah, if we want to do another session specifically on wavelets.
Lauren Infantino: I have some data that I can bring in as like an example.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yep, okay. You if you wanted to like share that to the drive. So.
Lauren Infantino: It? Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): I created an Emg filtering folder within the like shared Mc. Workshop. Sub folder.
Monica Daley (she, her): and you could drop your example. File there and then we can write some code to try a wavelet analysis on that. I also, I have some like test functions for the wavelets where you can like, you can create a signal with different frequency characteristics
Monica Daley (she, her): by specifying them with sine waves, and then analyze it with the wavelet analysis to see what it looks like. So just like, kind of understand? Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): they can create artificial data and then analyze it with the wavelets and see what it looks like. Right.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, make like a sine wave with multiple frequencies.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah. And then you can. So you can create, like your artificial signal that you're trying to like, decompose with the wavelets. And then.
Lauren Infantino: No way.
Monica Daley (she, her): That's on that. So we can, we can do another session. Probably after we get back from our conferences and stuff, because we're leaving yeah tomorrow. Yeah.
Lauren Infantino: That'll be fun, though.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then.
Lauren Infantino: Another one that would be interesting.
Monica Daley (she, her): And Vanson. Are there specific data types that you're
Monica Daley (she, her): going to need to work on filtering that you want to go over in another session?
Vanson Vu: I'm not sure. I think Lauren can answer that, but I wasn't really familiar with it too much. I'll just.
Monica Daley (she, her): Okay.
Vanson Vu: Here's how I can learn about it generally.
Monica Daley (she, her): So you'll have.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, that.
Monica Daley (she, her): What data types do you have? You have in your study.
Lauren Infantino: Really just have okay, this, like, general overview of filtering was is pretty much sufficient enough.
Lauren Infantino: It's not a huge complex. It's more like, yeah, figuring out if there's any noise components to get rid of and then filtering that out and creating an envelope on the data and then normalizing that data,
Monica Daley (she, her): Hmm.
Lauren Infantino: To some upper Max level.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah.
Lauren Infantino: Or ours. There's not much, I guess, the only one that I could see.
Lauren Infantino: which I know I sent you that like single
Monica Daley (she, her): The action potential. Yeah.
Lauren Infantino: The reflex. I guess. Characterize
Lauren Infantino: cause. I know there's initially like a lot of
Lauren Infantino: like a variable frequency in the Emg signal. And then this action potential and then more noise. And I guess.
Lauren Infantino: using this kind of method to get that so almost as if, like, it's a flat line for this like any noise. And then really, the action potential can be identified.
Lauren Infantino: the timing of it and the magnitude. But I think the things
Lauren Infantino: today can be applied to that easily.
Monica Daley (she, her): What I didn't mention is like there are other sources of electrical noise that might be
Monica Daley (she, her): noise that you pick up in those signals, too, like your heart rate might be picked up in the emg, right? So you know where there
Monica Daley (she, her): are other sources of noise to consider. So yeah, I think it's 1 thing you can do is like
Monica Daley (she, her): you can do an fft on like a section of the data. That is just the baseline data to get a characteristic of that.
Lauren Infantino: Right, right, yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): And then do an fft on the data that includes your signal to compare those 2. And so then you can kind of like, then go. Okay, this is the frequency band of my actual signal that I'm interested in, right.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah, I think more or less, ours might be
Lauren Infantino: more. We might be more inclined to create like a notch frequency for that action potential. And then just
Lauren Infantino: yeah, kind of.
Monica Daley (she, her): Depends on how much variation you get.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): It's usually going to be the slow
Monica Daley (she, her): motor units that are responding to a stretch reflex, I think. But there could.
Monica Daley (she, her): There's likely to be some variation among individuals, and the exact frequency, yeah.
Lauren Infantino: And I think, yeah, I think, using the fft 1st and then.
Lauren Infantino: Per individual, getting a frequency analysis to see where that action potential, wise, and then doing a notch filter just like.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yep, almost based on individuals.
Monica Daley (she, her): Well, it could be basically a bandpass filter, because a notch filter is basically the inverse of a bandpass. It's like where there's a.
Lauren Infantino: Specified.
Monica Daley (she, her): Range you're getting rid of. Yeah.
Lauren Infantino: Okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah. So I think what you'd want is basically like a very narrow bandpass filter to pull out that action potential frequency right?
Lauren Infantino: Yeah. And I think if we can figure out like the individual ranges like is within 10 hertz of like a frequency, then be like more confident to just like. Then pull all the data and band, pass it within this.
Monica Daley (she, her): Within that range.
Lauren Infantino: Didn't. Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah, that's reasonable.
Lauren Infantino: Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): It might be that the we we could play around with using the wavelets to pull that out because
Monica Daley (she, her): one of the differences between a wavelet analysis and a standard
Monica Daley (she, her): frequency. A filtering approach is that standard filters are really built around like sine wave approximations, and a wavelet like I have some code. That is basically where the wavelets are designed to have the shapes characteristic of action potentials.
Monica Daley (she, her): So they don't look exactly like sine waves.
Monica Daley (she, her): And so if you can find, like basically the right frequency of action potential
Monica Daley (she, her): from the wavelet kind of the band of wavelet, then you might be able to pull that out of the data even more precisely, potentially.
Lauren Infantino: Hmm, okay.
Monica Daley (she, her): Could play around with.
Lauren Infantino: Guys.
Monica Daley (she, her): That is a possibility too.
Lauren Infantino: Okay, yeah, I'm not like.
Lauren Infantino: I'm not a hundred percent sure, like the whole process of the wavelet stuff. But.
Lauren Infantino: I think. Yeah, it'd be interesting to learn a little bit more about it.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah. Okay, cool.
Monica Daley (she, her): All right. Well, we'll wrap up for today. Sorry, my computer decided it was done for today. Apparently.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah, all right. Well, thanks for coming. I saw somebody else logged in and then logged back out without
Monica Daley (she, her): chiming in. I feel like I hope, that they weren't intimidated, too intimidated to join.
Lauren Infantino: Oh!
Monica Daley (she, her): Oh, wow!
Monica Daley (she, her): All right. Well, I'll see you all later.
Monica Daley (she, her): Thanks.
Vanson Vu: Thank you.
Monica Daley (she, her): Bye.